Guide to the Journals of Horace Purdy MS 044 MS 044 MS 044
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Journals of Horace Purdy
1860-1905
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Purdy, Horace.
MS 044
0.25 Linear Feet 1 reel
Horace Purdy served in the 1st Connecticut Regiment during the Civil War. This is a collection of his journals from 1860 to 1905.
Provenance
Likely the microfilm was obtained by Truman Warner. The original diary was microfilmed in 1965 for the Scott Fanton Museum in Danbury, CT.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions. A digitized copy is currently being processed and is the preferred means of access.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Originals are held by the Scott Fanton Museum (Danbury Historical Society)
Historical/Biographical Note
The journals begin as Horace Purdy and wife Gussie begin their married life together in Danbury where they are active with their church and where they own a house with tenants. In 1860, Purdy was in the Wooster Light Guards militia company and appeared to have been the secretary. Gussie and Horace socialize frequently with Gussie's parents, Mrs. (referred to as Mother Griswold) and Father Griswold who was a prominent Methodist minister in the area. Purdy works in a hat shop and is busiest in the Winter and frequently suffers from headaches. He also works in his vegetable garden in the spring growing strawberries, lima beans, etc. His political leanings appear to have been Republican but there was much political activity among both parties in the run up to the local elections of 1860. Purdy reports on the activities of the "Wide Awakes" and it appears likely that he belonged to the group but he did not explicitly state that he was a member.
At the outbreak of the Civil War, Purdy joined the 1st Connecticut which was a 3 month enlistment regiment and was organized at Hartford in 1861. It served in the defenses of Washington, D.C. until it was used in an advance on Vienna and Falls Church, VA from June until July, 1861. It saw action in the Battle of Bull Run on July 21 and was mustered out of service on July 31, 1861.
After his term of service, Purdy returns to Danbury where he eventually transitions from being a hat finisher to selling insurance. Purdy reports on the minutia of his day, the weather and occasionally reports on national events with few editorial embellishments.
Civil War Soldiers and Sailors System. "1st Connecticut Infantry" [http://www.itd.nps.gov/cwss/regiments.cfm]
Scope and Content Note
Contains 6 volumes of Journals on one microfilm reel. Volumes 1 - 2 contain materials regarding Purdy's experiences in the Civil War; volumes 3 - 5 contain materials regarding his life from 1866 - 1870 and Volume 6 contains materials regarding his life from 1904 - Feb 9, 1905.
Arrangement
Journals are arranged chronologically.
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives.; Microfilm.; Danbury (Conn.); Connecticut History.; Journals.; Purdy, Horace.; Purdy, Horace.; Purdy Family.; Purdy, Horace.; Purdy, Horace.; United States. Army. Connecticut Infantry Regiment. 1st (1861).
- Volume 1: diary Jan 1860-Jun 1863
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1860, January 1860 (Reel 1, Entry 1)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1860, February 1860 (Reel 1, Entry 2)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1860, March 1860 (Reel 1, Entry 3)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1860, April 1860 (Reel 1, Entry 4)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1860, May 1860 (Reel 1, Entry 5)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1860, June 1860 (Reel 1, Entry 6)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1860, July 1860 (Reel 1, Entry 7)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1860, August 1860 (Reel 1, Entry 8)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1860, September 1860 (Reel 1, Entry 9)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1860, October 1860 (Reel 1, Entry 10)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1860, November 1860 (Reel 1, Entry 11)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1860, December 1860 (Reel 1, Entry 12)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1861, January 1861 (Reel 1, Entry 13)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1861, February 1861 (Reel 1, Entry 14)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1861, March 1861 (Reel 1, Entry 15)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1861, April 1861 (Reel 1, Entry 16)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1861, May 1861 (Reel 1, Entry 17)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1861, June 1861 (Reel 1, Entry 18)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1861, July 1861 (Reel 1, Entry 19)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1861, August 1861 (Reel 1, Entry 20)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1861, September 1861 (Reel 1, Entry 21)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1861, October 1861 (Reel 1, Entry 22)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1861, November 1861 (Reel 1, Entry 23)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1861, December 1861 (Reel 1, Entry 24)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1862, January 1862 (Reel 1, Entry 25)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1862, February 1862 (Reel 1, Entry 26)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1862, March 1862 (Reel 1, Entry 27)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1862, April 1862 (Reel 1, Entry 28)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1862, May 1862 (Reel 1, Entry 29)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1862, June 1862 (Reel 1, Entry 30)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1862, July 1862 (Reel 1, Entry 31)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1862, August 1862 (Reel 1, Entry 32)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1862, September 1862 (Reel 1, Entry 33)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1862, October 1862 (Reel 1, Entry 34)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1862, November 1862 (Reel 1, Entry 35)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1862, December 1862 (Reel 1, Entry 36)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1863, January 1863 (Reel 1, Entry 37)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1863, February 1863 (Reel 1, Entry 38)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1863, March 1863 (Reel 1, Entry 39)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1863, April 1863 (Reel 1, Entry 40)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1863, May 1863 (Reel 1, Entry 41)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1863, June 1863 (Reel 1, Entry 42)
- Volume 2 Mar 1864-Dec 1865
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1864, March 1864 (Reel 1, Entry 43)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1864, April 1864 (Reel 1, Entry 44)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1864, May 1864 (Reel 1, Entry 45)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1864, June 1864 (Reel 1, Entry 46)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1864, July 1864 (Reel 1, Entry 47)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1864, August 1864 (Reel 1, Entry 48)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1864, September 1864 (Reel 1, Entry 49)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1864, October 1864 (Reel 1, Entry 50)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1864, November 1864 (Reel 1, Entry 51)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1864, December 1864 (Reel 1, Entry 52)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1865, December 1865 (Reel 1, Entry 53)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1865, January 1865 (Reel 1, Entry 54)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1865, February 1865 (Reel 1, Entry 55)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1865, March 1865 (Reel 1, Entry 56)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1865, April 1865 (Reel 1, Entry 57)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1865, May 1865 (Reel 1, Entry 58)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1865, June 1865 (Reel 1, Entry 59)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1865, July 1865 (Reel 1, Entry 60)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1865, August 1865 (Reel 1, Entry 61)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1865, September 1865 (Reel 1, Entry 62)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1865, October 1865 (Reel 1, Entry 63)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1865, November 1865 (Reel 1, Entry 64)
- Volume 3 Jan 1866-Jan 1867
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1866, January 1866 (Reel 1, Entry 65)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1866, February 1866 (Reel 1, Entry 66)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1866, March 1866 (Reel 1, Entry 67)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1866, April 1866 (Reel 1, Entry 68)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1866, May 1866 (Reel 1, Entry 69)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1866, June 1866 (Reel 1, Entry 70)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1866, July 1866 (Reel 1, Entry 71)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1866, August 1866 (Reel 1, Entry 72)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1866, September 1866 (Reel 1, Entry 73)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1866, October 1866 (Reel 1, Entry 74)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1866, November 1866 (Reel 1, Entry 75)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1866, December 1866 (Reel 1, Entry 76)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1867, January 1867 (Reel 1, Entry 77)
- Volume 4 Feb 1867-Aug 1868
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1867, February 1867 (Reel 1, Entry 78)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1867, March 1867 (Reel 1, Entry 79)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1867, April 1867 (Reel 1, Entry 80)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1867, May 1867 (Reel 1, Entry 81)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1867, June 1867 (Reel 1, Entry 82)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1867, July 1867 (Reel 1, Entry 83)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1867, October 1867 (Reel 1, Entry 84)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1867, November 1867 (Reel 1, Entry 85)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1867, December 1867 (Reel 1, Entry 86)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1868, January 1868 (Reel 1, Entry 87)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1868, February 1868 (Reel 1, Entry 88)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1868, March 1868 (Reel 1, Entry 89)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1868, April 1868 (Reel 1, Entry 90)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1868, May 1868 (Reel 1, Entry 91)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1868, June 1868 (Reel 1, Entry 92)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1868, July 1868 (Reel 1, Entry 93)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1868, August 1868 (Reel 1, Entry 94)
- Volume 5 Aug 1868-Jun 1870
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1868, September 1868 (Reel 1, Entry 95)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1868, October 1868 (Reel 1, Entry 96)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1868, November 1868 (Reel 1, Entry 97)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1868, December 1868 (Reel 1, Entry 98)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1869, January 1869 (Reel 1, Entry 99)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1869, February 1869 (Reel 1, Entry 100)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1869, March 1869 (Reel 1, Entry 101)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1869, April 1869 (Reel 1, Entry 102)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1869, May 1869 (Reel 1, Entry 103)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1869, June 1869 (Reel 1, Entry 104)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1869, July 1869 (Reel 1, Entry 105)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1869, August 1869 (Reel 1, Entry 106)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1869, September 1869 (Reel 1, Entry 107)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1869, October 1869 (Reel 1, Entry 108)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1869, November 1869 (Reel 1, Entry 109)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1869, December 1869 (Reel 1, Entry 110)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1870, January 1870 (Reel 1, Entry 111)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1870, February 1870 (Reel 1, Entry 112)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1870, March 1870 (Reel 1, Entry 113)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1870, April 1870 (Reel 1, Entry 114)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1870, May 1870 (Reel 1, Entry 115)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1870, June 1870 (Reel 1, Entry 116)
- Volume 6 Feb 1904-Feb 1905
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1904, February 1904 (Reel 1, Entry 117)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1904, March 1904 (Reel 1, Entry 118)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1904, April 1904 (Reel 1, Entry 119)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1904, May 1904 (Reel 1, Entry 120)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1904, June 1904 (Reel 1, Entry 121)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1904, July 1904 (Reel 1, Entry 122)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1904, August 1904 (Reel 1, Entry 123)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1904, September 1904 (Reel 1, Entry 124)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1904, October 1904 (Reel 1, Entry 125)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1904, November 1904 (Reel 1, Entry 126)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1904, December 1904 (Reel 1, Entry 127)
  - Horace Purdy journal entries, 1905, January 1905 (Reel 1, Entry 128)